<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<chapter id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
    This book provides an introduction to creating and nurturing
    communities of contributors.  This is a core part of Red Hat's
    mission, as manifested in the many communities where Red Hat is an
    active contributor.
  </para>
  <para>
    Red Hat employs contributors who work directly in upstream
    development on all parts of the open source architecture stack,
    from the Linux kernel to the thinnest skin of Ajax4Jsf.  How these
    people interact with their communities is the first part of how
    Red Hat influences the growth of community.
  </para>
  <para>
    The qualities of the interaction of each individual contributor
    are as different as any human-to-human interaction.  Over the
    course of time, these many interactions distill to a set of
    guiding principles that help us with the community growth and
    nurturing.
  </para>
  <para>
    Red Hat has collective community wisdom.
  </para>
  <para>
    We also have particular skill and luck in being thought and action
    leaders in many open communities.  It has all been done in an
    open, ad hoc fashion, and it hasn't been written down before.
  </para>
  <para>
    So this book is a capturing of that distilled knowledge.  It is
    also an active document, as that knowledge grows and changes, so
    do the contents of this book.
  </para>
  <para>
    This book is small and written on a wiki to facilitate
    collaboration and growth.  If you have ideas to improve the
    <citetitle>The Open Source Way</citetitle>, you are encouraged to
    just start writing it down.  Use a page's "discussion" tab to
    access the talk page.
  </para>
  <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-What_this_book_is">
    <title>What this book is</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>A book that:</para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem><para>... describes a principle</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>... explains how to implement
	it</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>... and gives real world examples.</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>A thin reference guide to richer, thicker
      works that explain Big Principles in Lots of Fancy
      Words.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>An open how-to manual, initially authored
      by the Red Hat
      <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Community_Architecture">
      Community Architecture</ulink> team.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Useful for much more than just code --
      art/design, documentation, marketing, translation, IT, and
      so on</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-What_it_is_not">
    <title>What it is not</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Comprehensive for the sake of inclusion.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>We are focused on slim and useful.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>Overly repetitive of content already said and
      available elsewhere as free and open.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Build on the work of others via the power of
	reference.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>Boring.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-What_it_is_influenced_by">
    <title>What it is influenced by</title>
    <para>
      There are some very comprehensive, thorough, and useful works, such as:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><citetitle><ulink
      url="http://producingoss.com/en/index.html">Producing Open
      Source Software</ulink></citetitle></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><citetitle><ulink
      url="http://www.ewenger.com/pub/pubcultivatingbook.htm">
      Cultivating Communities of Practice</ulink></citetitle>.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      More influencers and good reads are found in <xref
      linkend="The_Open_Source_Way-Books_you_should_read"/> and <xref
      linkend="The_Open_Source_Way-Data_and_references"/>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Essential_terminology_or_Read_this_even_if_you_think_you_know_what_it_means">
    <title>Essential terminology or 'Read this even if you think you
    know what it means'</title>
    <note>
      <title>This section is growing ...</title>
      <para>
	This section is growing for a while as
	the <citetitle>The Open Source Way</citetitle> is written and
	terms need defining.
      </para>
    </note>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Community">
      <title>Community</title>
      <para>
	When people talk about community, they may be talking
	about very different things:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>People who <emphasis
	role="italics">use</emphasis> something</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>People who <emphasis
	role="italics">like</emphasis> something</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>People who <emphasis
	role="italics">advocate</emphasis> for a
	technology</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>People who <emphasis role="italics">enable
	others</emphasis> to use something</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>People who <emphasis role="italics">contribute
	to improve</emphasis> something</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>... and so on.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	When we talk about community in the <citetitle>The Open Source
	Way</citetitle>, we mean the community of contributors who are
	a superset to all other communities.  The ones who, by getting
	things done, make it possible for many, many more to get much,
	much more done.
      </para>
      <para>
	This is the group of people who form intentionally and
	spontaneously around something important to them.  It includes
	the people who use or benefit from the project, those who
	participate and share the project to wider audiences, and the
	contributors who are essential to growth and survival.
      </para>
      <para>
	Contributors are the oxygen.  Without it, the animal chokes
	and dies.
      </para>
      <important>
	<title>The community that contributes to improve something
	...</title>
	<para>
	  The community that contributes to improve something is
	  the one that defines the technology and the next generation
	  of users, advocates, and enablers.
	</para>
      </important>
    </section>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Tactics">
      <title>Tactics</title>
      <para>
	This is derived from military terminology.  The common example
	is a group of soldiers who work with a squad leader to take
	and secure a hill.
      </para>
      <para>
	<firstterm>Tactics</firstterm> are the ideas, plans, methods,
	and means used to accomplish a goal.  That is, tactics are the
	maneuvers used to achieve an objective that is set by
	strategy.
      </para>
      <para>
	In Fedora, the strict yet clever <ulink
	url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Packaging">packaging
	guidelines</ulink> are a strong-arm tactic that enforces the
	Fedora strategy of good packaging of only free and open source
	software.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Strategy">
      <title>Strategy</title>
      <para>
	<firstterm>Strategy</firstterm> focuses on everything from
	which hill to secure, to deciding which miltary campaigns to
	engage in.
      </para>
      <para>
	A term from military science, strategy is the focus of the
	command group.  Strategy focuses on setting goals and which
	groups can obtain the goals.
      </para>
      <para>
	Once the "who, what, where, when, and why" is decided, tactics
	takes over as the "how".
      </para>
      <para>
	The Fedora strategy of creating and supporting only FLOSS is
	derived from the culture of the community combined with a
	pragmatic view of the legal and business landscape.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Planets_and_blogs">
      <title>Planets and blogs</title>
      <para>
	A <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blog">blog</ulink>
	is a mix of personal and project writing that comes from a
	participant or contributor.
      </para>
      <para>
	The idea of a <firstterm>blog planet</firstterm> is to show
	the width and depth of personalities in a community, and what
	they are doing.
      </para>
      <para>
	It intentionally allows for personal expression.  In other
	words, the content is not all community specific.  It is
	sometimes wildly off topic.
      </para>
      <para>
	The <ulink url="http://planet.fedoraproject.org">Fedora
	Planet</ulink> is a good example, with blogs aggregated from
	willing contributors.  People add themselves to the planet,
	and it is a mix of languages, topics, skill levels, and
	project interest.  All aspects of the Fedora Project are
	covered there on a daily basis, with a wide variety of
	contributors from Packaging, Art and Design, Marketing,
	upstream development, and so on.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Leaderless_organizations">
      <title>Leaderless organizations</title>
      <para>
	A leaderless organization is
	<firstterm>decentralized</firstterm>, meaning it does not rely
	upon a central authority for leadership, strategy, or tactics.
	Being decentralized makes it easier to heal, faster to respond
	and innovate, and more able to grow in scale.
      </para>
      <para>
	An example of a large leaderless organization is the Internet.
	Not just the set of agreements that makes the structure work,
	but all the way down to the wire protocols that route around
	damage in the network, such as when a backhoe slices through a
	fiber link between two ISPs.
      </para>
      <para>
	In projects, <ulink
	url="http://wikipedia.org">Wikipedia</ulink> is a
	decentralized organization, while the
	<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Encyclop%C3%A6dia_Britannica">
	  Encyclopaedia Brittanica</ulink> is a classic centralized
	  organization.
      </para>
      <para>
	The idea of the leaderless organization is put forth in the
	book <ulink url="http://www.starfishandspider.com/">The
	Starfish and The Spider</ulink>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Version_control">
      <title>Version control</title>
      <para>
	Version control is the comfortable insurance that means you
	can sleep soundly at night.
      </para>
      <para>
	A <firstterm>version control system (VCS)</firstterm> keeps
	track of the differences in versions of content.  Properly
	implemented, it is nearly disaster proof.
      </para>
      <para>
	When a document is saved in to a VCS, the difference between
	the current saved copy and the one just before it is stored.
	The same occurred at all previous saves.  This makes it
	possible to restore a document to any point in its save
	history.  It is also possible to return to a previous save
	point and start a new pathway of saves from there.  In code
	this is called <firstterm>branching</firstterm>, with the
	original code in the central <firstterm>trunk</firstterm>.
      </para>
      <para>
	When you work with a web-based tool to write, edit, and
	display a document, you are using version control.  All
	content management systems and wikis use a form of version
	control to capture and display the differences between edits.
      </para>
      <para>
	Version control provides noisy reporting.  Anyone who is
	interested or able may watch the stream of changes, or derive
	reports from them.  Watching and commenting on version saves
	as they occur is a hallmark of the open source methodology.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Content_v._code_repositories">
      <title>Content v. code repositories</title>
      <para>
	Code is a specialized form of content.  There are many
	similarities between repositories of code and content.  The
	major difference is in the tools.
      </para>
      <para>
	Code repository tools focus on centralized or decentralized
	development of the code.  The ability to return to a point in
	time and branch from there is essential.
      </para>
      <para>
	Content repository tools also include the ability to return to
	previous points in a documents save history.  They also
	include management tools, such as team automation in
	MediaWiki, and workflow, publishing, and lifecycle components
	in a content management system (CMS).
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Open_collaboration_tools">
      <title>Open collaboration tools</title>
      <para>
	These are examples of open collaboration tools used in the
	open source communities.  The same or similar tools apply to
	any online community of practice.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>What is a wiki?</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>What is a mailing list?</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>What is IRC?</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Open_marketing">
      <title>Open marketing</title>
      <para>
	This is marketing done entirely in the open, no secret
	discussions on brand tactics behind the Wizard's curtain.  You
	talk about your strengths, weaknesses, brand position, and so
	forth as an ongoing open discussion.
      </para>
      <para>
	Central to this are social media tools.  Some are used for
	discussions, some are for information dispersal, but any
	vector is a potential for learning and spreading the word.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Blogging planet or otherwise aggregated feed
	of all contributors</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Publicly displayed and discussed content and
	code committing</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Always being watched</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>All mailing list
	  traffic</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>All IRC logs</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>All voice sessions logged and available</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>100% totally accountable
	  discussions</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>Radically transparent</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Fundamental_rule_-_do_not_bash_competitors">
	<title>Fundamental rule - do not bash competitors</title>
	<para>
	  In fact, ignore them when talking about your project.  Why
	  waste the attention you've got on your project to point
	  attention at something else?
	</para>
      </section>
      <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Fundamental_rule_-_be_radically_transparent">
	<title>Fundamental rule - be radically transparent</title>
	<para>
	  There is no such thing as too much information.  Everything
	  you can legally say, you should be saying.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Don't use this as an excuse to be verbose or disorganized.
	</para>
      </section>
      <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Fundamental_rule_-_explain_what_you_know_and_how_you_know_it">
	<title>Fundamental rule - explain what you know and how you
	know it</title>
	<para>
	  In the general category of being honest, spend some time
	  with revealing sources and means. Bad numbers are everywhere
	  in software and communities.  Make sure your numbers are
	  real and provable.
	</para>
	<para>
	  This also falls in the general methodology of thinking
	  like a scientist.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="The_Open_Source_Way-Introduction-Science">
      <title>Science</title>
      <para>
	We may all be social artists in our communities, but in the end, our understanding of this is all driven by science.
      </para>
      <para>
	There is an active feedback loop happening right now:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem><para>Scientific method wildly successful and
	bringing forth new, life altering ideas and innovations
	...</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Scientific method is a direct parent of the
	open source methodology ...</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Open source way practiced in business/private
	sector ...</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Influences academia ...</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Influences public/government
	...</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Funds science and supports innovation
	...</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Iterating through more ideas for the Great
	Ones ...</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>(Back to top)</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
	The open source way is breaking through to help make new ideas
	happen ... in organizations that brought us the ideas of free
	government and free, public education ... ideas that were
	revolutionary and evolutionary in the 19th century ... that
	fueled a century of innovation ... and are now getting
	refueled by new ways of openly collaborating on
	infrastructures of freedom.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
